<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Harsh's blog</title><link>https://hargup.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://hargup.github.io/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2014 17:59:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola &lt;http://getnikola.com/&gt;</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Week 1 and Week 2</title><link>https://hargup.github.io/posts/week-1-and-week-2.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi, As I told you about in the previous post, My work for this summer will be
improving the current equation solvers of sympy. There are basically three
thing I'll have to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create a basic set infrastructure for solvers to return sets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rewrite the current solvers to be clean and robust.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the top of 1 and 2 write new solvers and function, they will returning
   and handling all the solutions of equations like &lt;code&gt;sin(x) == 0&lt;/code&gt; and a general
   singularity finder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can look at the details in my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/GSoC-2014-Application-Harsh-Gupta:-Solvers."&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A started working on the sets module in the community bonding period, basically
writing a set difference class at &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/7462"&gt;this
PR&lt;/a&gt; , I try to get it merged by the
end of this week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set are a pretty general mathematical constructs, and you can solve a lot of
hard problems if you could compute general set operations. The whole number
theory can be defined in terms of sets. So, computing general set operations,
e.g, intersection, unions is pretty hard problem too and we should not aim to
do all them.  In a meeting with Matthew and Sergey we discussed that it would
    be better if complete the part 2 first. It will give a general idea about
    what capabilities of sets we need.  Also some sets problems can be reduced
    to equations and vice versa.  &lt;!-- Explain --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've started working on the univariate solvers &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/7523"&gt;at
PR&lt;/a&gt;.  My aim for this
week will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Completing the rational solvers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting the open PR for the sets merged.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>sympy</category><category>GSoC</category><guid>https://hargup.github.io/posts/week-1-and-week-2.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2014 11:45:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GSoC 2014 with Sympy</title><link>https://hargup.github.io/posts/gsoc-2014-with-sympy.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi, I'm Harsh Gupta an undergrad student at IIT Kharagpur, I've been accepted
this year for the Google Summer of Code program with Sympy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, What is a Google Summer of Code?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Summer of Code is a program by Google to promote opensource development.
In this program Google pays handsome stipends to students to work for various opensource
organisations. In the application phase the students have to write proposals to
the organisations describing the projects they want to do
and how do they fit for it. If the proposal is accepted the student is provided
with a mentor and with the guidance of the mentor the student has to complete
the project in the given timeline. You can look at my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/GSoC-2014-Application-Harsh-Gupta:-Solvers"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;.
I proposed to work on improving the current equation solvers in
Sympy. My mentors for the Project are &lt;a href="https://github.com/mrocklin"&gt;Matthew Rocklin&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://github.com/skirpichev"&gt;Sergey B Kipirchev&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A word about Sympy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://sympy.org/"&gt;Sympy&lt;/a&gt; is a pure python library for symbolic computation. Symbolic
computation is similar to the maths you do by hands and it differs from
numerical computations. More about Symbolic and Numerical computation in
some other post. Sympy has been created by hundreds of contributors starting from 2006.
It has an awesome developer
community and we encourage outsiders to contribute and get their hands dirty with
the code. What do you need to start contributing? Some python skills and little
patience. Download the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy"&gt;latest development code&lt;/a&gt;.
Go through the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/Development-workflow"&gt;development workflow&lt;/a&gt;.
Find something to work on from the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues?labels=Easy+to+Fix&amp;amp;milestone=&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;state=open"&gt;EasyToFix Issues&lt;/a&gt;.
Code it and send us a &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/articles/using-pull-requests"&gt;pull request&lt;/a&gt;. Happy Coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll give a brief about the project aim and current state of work in the next post.
I'm looking forward for a great summer with Sympy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://hargup.github.io/posts/gsoc-2014-with-sympy.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 19:24:22 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>