<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Harsh Gupta</title><link>http://hargup.in/</link><description>Personal website of Harsh Gupta</description><atom:link href="http://hargup.in/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 18:36:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Normalization of Deviation</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/wtf_wtf_wtf.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;span&gt;&lt;!-- url: http://danluu.com/wat/ --&gt;
&lt;!-- title: Normalization of Deviation --&gt;
&lt;!-- date --&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/wtf_wtf_wtf.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Failed Wikipedia</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_wikipedia.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributors follow power law, the median number of contributors is 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_wikipedia.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>once_upon_a_jihad</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/once_upon_a_jihad.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This essay provides a facinating account of westners who leave their homes to
fight in middle east, Afghanistan and other places to fight for "jihad". The
highlights that for these people going and fighting in a war is pretty much
like a personal fairly tail&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/once_upon_a_jihad.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>economic_inequality</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/economic_inequality.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Paul started off saying he is interested in inequality because he created
I was half expecting him to "this is what I've done wrong and I want to fix
it". Unfortunately it was another essay to justify "undeserved" wealth in the
hands of startup founders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul's essay fails to look at the dynamics of power and money. The amount of
money someone has is often a proxy for political power in the hand of someone.
Increasing inequality amounts to increasing disbalance in political power.
Concentration of political power is problematic because the powerful influence
things in their in their favor knowingly or unknowlingly ignoring the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue that Paul fails to address is the reason for economic inequality.
The wealth of someone grows exponentially, the money someone has the easier it
will be for them to make even more money. That has nothing to do with how much
"deserving" they are or how much wealth they have. Sure your startups have
helped the world, but that doesn't mean they "deserve" all the wealth they
have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have answer to the problem of inequality, but this doesn't mean the
problem doesn't exist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/economic_inequality.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>digital_activism</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/digital_activism.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology by itself is not enough we need to leverage it to create the
  effect we want it to have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lumia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Democracy OS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/digital_activism.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>bad_feminism</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/bad_feminism.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; All these bad-feminist articles do is reinforce the belief that feminism is the
&amp;gt; purview of a legion of judgy women policing the mostly superficial choices of
&amp;gt; others.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/bad_feminism.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why isn't the NSA a hot topic in the US elections?</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_isnt_nsa_a_hot_topic_in_us_elections.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The article talks about how NSA surveillance should be one of the topics of the
US presidential election but isn't. It compares the situation with Germany
where the population is very privacy conscious. It brings out important facts
but doesn't connect them well, it says that German population is privacy
conscious because of the human rights violation by Eastern Block Germany and
earlier by the Nazi secret police, but it reaches the conclusion that
surveillance isn't a hot topic because it is very nuanced and doesn't make good
catch phrase. But every topic is nuanced if you look deep enough and every
issue has only one answer on the surface. Politicians don't generally aim to
change the norm during the election but rather try to attract a sect of people
who already agrees with her/him. So the question here should be why does the
German population care and US doesn't. Well one of the answers can be history
as the author already mentioned, there have been thought policing in the
McCarthy era too but not sure about the extent to which it affected the white
population. Another important factor should be the corporate influence in
politics and maybe media in America compared to Germany. Corporate surveillance
goes hand in hand in government surveillance, if corporates doesn't support an
issue the issue remains unattractive for the politicians. Also it would be an
interesting exercise to study the relation between the profits a parent company
make through breaches of privacy and its coverage on surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_isnt_nsa_a_hot_topic_in_us_elections.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 15:15:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>lessons_from_brain_scans</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/lessons_from_brain_scans.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;SPECT Scans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Healthy scans are syematic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;OCD front part is active
* Seizer too much activity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: ERROR/3 (&lt;tt class="docutils"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, line 8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unexpected indentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Phycatrists don't look at the organ they treat
* Same symptoms can have very different brain scans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: ERROR/3 (&lt;tt class="docutils"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, line 10)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unexpected indentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mild Traumatic Brain Injury
* Behavior is a expression of problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;People who do bad things often do have bad brains.
* Crime evaluation and treatement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="system-message"&gt;
&lt;p class="system-message-title"&gt;System Message: ERROR/3 (&lt;tt class="docutils"&gt;&amp;lt;string&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;, line 16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unexpected indentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NFL causes brain damage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/lessons_from_brain_scans.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2016 15:39:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why you'll fail to have a good career</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_you_ll_fail_to_have_a_good_career.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luck&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genius&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weird&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nice normal people don't have passion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest vs Passion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Velcro vs UFT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I value human relationships more than accomplishment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use your children as a shield&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was afraid to pursue it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If only I had&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched this because a friend recommend this to me. This has nothing new to
offer. Cut out the rhetoric and it didn't said a lot of either. It mainly
summarized the "excuses" people give on why they failed to have a "great
career". They fear they aren't lucky enough, they fear coming out as weird to
others, they say "nice and normal people don't passion". And then he says
people use children as shield and don't work hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying overcome your fear doesn't make you overcome it, Why have a "great"
career at all? People do fuck up relationships for accomplishment, people do
have to take care of their familes and kids and their are real constraints
because of them. It also doesn't define what is a great career and what does it
look like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find zero or rather negative value in this kinds of talk. It provides no
solutions nor does it provide any clarity or new insights on the problem. All
it does is to make people without "great careers" feel like lazy blob and it
provides people with "great career" a kind of entitlement making them feel like
they "deserved" it and they are somehow above those without a "great career".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- First of all it doesn't define what is great career, --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luck &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; is a factor which decides who will have a "great career", rather I
should say privilege is a great deciding factor, ofcouse not to say it is the
only factor. Because luck or randomness is a factor doesn't mean you cannot
improve your chances, but this talk gives no insight on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are real constraints in making a great career, one of the reason of
the glass ceiling is kids and the fact they have to work dabble shift, one at
the office and other at home. Then there are people for whom there is really a
very little margin of error and people who don't have strong backgrounds and
people who don't have a great support structure. The risk taking ability of
someone is often because of the external factors rather than the internals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it encourages and motivates that's great, but if you say it is your fault
that you are not pursuing your passion, then fuck off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people trying to purse their passions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Careerism??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fuck it I don't feel like writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="cut-out"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Cut Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When some like this guy tells people from outside that
they are making excuses, how do you know they aren't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_you_ll_fail_to_have_a_good_career.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 09:26:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Normalization of Deviation</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/normailization_of_deviation.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a pretty well written post about how very messed up practices end up
normalized. The answer is a weird combinatin of over optimism, rationalization
and adaption. And when a messed up practice gets normalized it is very hard to
see what's wrong with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very simply solution that Atul Gawande talked about in the Checklist
Manifesto is to have a checklist. In the book he compared the medical sector
and infrastucture/construction sector. Both fields are immensely complex but
medicial practitioners often end up making terrible mistakes, which includes
cases like the one where a surgen forgot her equipment in the patient, where as
in construction error which have any harm to human life are very very rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you don't have checklist for every small thing, and Atul provided a
guideline to making checklist, I don't clearly remember and I should go and
read the sections of the book again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checklists are useful because they end up freeing your mind from the
unnecessary boring detail. there are also other cases I can think of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to apply a rule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where the rewards or looses of doing something occur only in long term, we
tend to ignore the long term result and focus on instant gratification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always and never rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The projects the complete counts and not the one you start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formalization leads to gramatization, when a formal structure is in place it is
harder see things in informal terms or whatever that doesn't fall into that
formal structure tends to get ignored. A very clear example will be case where
peolple who have only learned about information transfer uses of language tend
find phatic usuages like that of small talk "useless".  But as it evident from
the use of term phatic, the way we with problems of formalization is more
formalization trying to capture things which weren't captured earlier, ofcourse
that formalization also leaves something. But as it said in Statistics, all
models are false but some are useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/normailization_of_deviation.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 18:46:01 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>