<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Harsh Gupta</title><link>http://hargup.in/</link><description>Personal website of Harsh Gupta</description><atom:link href="http://hargup.in/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 07:41:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Machine Learning isn't Kaggle Competition</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/ml_isn_t_kaggle_competition.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Kaggle is a machine learning contest platform, where the participants are given
a machine learning problem, a training dataset, an evaluation criterion and
they have to build the best model. But, while doing machine learning in
production these things comes much later, you have to first define the Business
Problem very clearly, determine if it is even a right ML problem or not. Get
the right data, clean it up, determine the right metrics, do a lot of
engineering part to put it in product and keep it running. The Kaggle
Competition part is much smaller and much less significant than people would
imagine.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/ml_isn_t_kaggle_competition.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2018 07:30:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>"On Thinking and Stimulated Thinking"</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/stimulated_thinking.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a distinction between two modes of working, one is the "explore
mode", you need to put in a lot of effort, and be concious while you are doing
something. This which occurs while you are learning something, say learning to
drive a car or bike. Other mode is the "habit mode" where you are able to do
something, effortlessly without thinking because you have done it so many
times, like riding a bike after you have learned it, or even writing or typing
which I am doing now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of the article is that "real thinking" happens in the "explore
mode", you are deliberate, you are explicative, you are curious, you (at least
mentally) try a lot of things out and reach a conclusion. What a lot of people
end up doing is they go do "stimulated thinking", which often looks and acts
like thinking but is actually in the "habit mode".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Stimulated thinking" is dangerous because is not flexible, it cannot
understand things deeply or see how they will change if the context will
change. Simply "Stimulated thinking" is not thinking and should not pass as so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore mode requires action and reaction in an environment, where the person
exploring something decides how to act and then modifies her behavior on the
basis of the reaction of the environment. Habit "knows" what is the reaction
will be so it behaves accordingly in fixed patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Author claims that so much of our learning process today is about broadcast,
not action and reaction or learning by trying something out. Education is
formal broadcast, so is TV or social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see parallels here with "Amusing Ourselves to Death" where Niel Postman (in
part) talks that TV consumption is passive, from few to many, there is no
creativity and interactivity for the consumers of television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noam Chomsky also said "You just don't let a book pass from the front of your
eyes". Well to avoid stimulated thinking I am here again writing webnotes. It
takes effort but I guess after sometime I'll be in the habit of putting in this
effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just clarifying that there is nothing wrong with habits per se, I'm able to
type only after I have deliberately learned this habit of typing and without
it, a lot of my effort would have gone into the act of typing itself instead
thinking about what I am writing. The problem is which thinking that you are
thinking but you are actually not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>thought</category><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/stimulated_thinking.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 19:04:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Currents of Fear</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/currents_of_fear.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This transcript of news sessions was about fears of cancer from electro
magnetic radiation from power lines. It was pretty long, but interesting. I
came here from the article on "Texas Sharpshooter fallacy". the fallacy goes
like this. If you take a lot of random points then some of them will cluster,
so a Texan can randomly shoot in his backyard and then draw circle around a
cluster which he is very likely to find, and say "yay I'm a sharp shooter".
Well the fallacy is more general. If you take a lot of random data you'll find
some pattern, definitely. Assuming cancer is randomly distributed, some of
these people getting cancer will be in a small geographic area and of some of
these groups you'll find power lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the Swedish study did was they tested for 800 different types of
alingments that might be linked to radiations by power lines and they find
Lukemia is correlated and a news agency published it. Susequent studies in
Sweden and elsewhere found such effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many speakers in the discussion and there is this particular guy who
speaks for protecting people from radiation though power lines. His argument is
similar to Taleb's precautionary principle, that human body is complex and we
don't understand it enough hence we should be careful. I compare it with
Taleb's argument on GMO, though the important differences is that in GMO the
harm is large and systemic. The harm is not that someone will fall ill from
eating GMO but that GMO can disrupt the whole ecosystem and we don't know
enough of biology to be sure that they won't. Another difference is about size
of effect, in the power lines case, the health effects if present are likely to
be small because otherwise we would have known them, though in GMO the
disruptions can be very very large, I remember some episodes from discovery
channel where introduction of a new specify in an unhabitat completely
distroyed the habitat. The GMO plant can grow quickly, interbred with other non
GMO plants nearby and spread pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect size part is very important. There can be millions of things which
"can be" negatively affecting your health according to VastuShastra the
architecture of your house affects your health (maybe though light and
ventilation), the material of your utensils might make a difference, the
lightint you use at your home might make a difference, the method of
preperation of food makes a difference, there are all sorts of things and all
sorts of reasons you might think these thigns might make a difference. Because
there are so many thigns, it is impossible to take care of everyone of them,
and you cannot know if the effects are real (without taking humgous effort of
carrying very long, longitudal experimental studies), so maybe just ignore all
these and focus on things which have stronger effect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/currents_of_fear.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2018 18:44:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Community vs Compliance</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/community_vs_compliance.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This a very interesting discussion about GPL law suits and GPL enforcement. The
main point of debate is whether to use law suits to enforce GPL or not. Both of
the parties agree that having upstream contributions and user freedoms are
important but disagree about the particular methods to pursue that goal. The
side which pushes for law suits or threats argue that otherwise companies won't
comply, we don't get the code back and users loose on freedom. The other side
argues that law suits or their threats turn companies into law suits turn
companies into enemies. They are less likely to coorperate, meaning worse
software. Instead the way should be through internal negotiations, and changing
the culture from inside, companies eventually do contribute upstream they also
benifit from it and also because the law requires them to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal opinion is that GPL is important, and the possibility of existance
of a law suit. If a company is going very antagonistic there needs to be a law
suits because otherwise when the companies know that no one realistic change of
law suit then GPL is powerless. Stallman himself gave examples of cases where
they were able to get GPL compliance simply about asking companies to do and
telling them that they are legally required to do so. So to me the question is
really about threshold, not the fact that they should be law suit or not,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway as Linus says it is often easier to change things by working with your
opponents rathan working against them but against them should appear like a
realistic senario when things don't work out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/community_vs_compliance.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 21:38:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Streetlight Effect: A metaphor for knowledge and ignorance</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/streetlight_effect.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This was a fascinating piece about Streetlight Effect and using it a as
metaphor to describe knowledge and ignorance. The really interesting bit was
where author described totalitarianism as something where there is only one
view point be it of boilerplate Marxism or free market capitalism or anything.
The totalitarian view point assumes that their framework can explain it all and
everything else. Totalitarianism is the like the streetlight where you try to
find all your answers but they don't exist there. The opposite of
totalitarianism isn't another view point but darkness where good and bad aren't
well defined and where the difference of between truth and false is not known.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/streetlight_effect.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 06:12:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Another rant about academia and open source</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/another_rant_about_academia_and_open_source.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; You can win in two ways: you can research something that helps somebody beat
&amp;gt; somebody else up or consume more, so that they give you funding. Or you can win
&amp;gt; by not losing, by pulling some wild theoretical stunt that puts you out of
&amp;gt; range of everybody else so that they can’t come after you. You become good at
&amp;gt; critiquing things in ways that sound smart, and tell people who disagree with
&amp;gt; you that they haven’t read your cannon. You hope that if they call your bluff
&amp;gt; and read it, they will be so converted by the experience that they will leave
&amp;gt; you alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This para drives home the point at so many levels. This is also something I
need to be really careful while doing inter disciplinary research. Being from
computational sciences I can use tools which no one in the humanities area
understand and it will be trying to answer questions which no one in the area
of the computational science cares about. So you'll be virtually unbeatable,
which is a really bad place to be in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping your research in open and helping access it as much as possible not
only increases the value of your research but also gives a proof that what you
are working on is something somebody cares about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/another_rant_about_academia_and_open_source.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 05:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reason as memetic immune disorder</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/reason_as_memetic_immune_disorder.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This was a very interesting analysis by PhilGoetz how "reason" can be thought
of a memetic immune disorder. The idea is that people have lot of belives which
might come from religion or tradition or culture. Since belives are often very
general, they might not generalize well. In a situtation where live with that
belive for a long time with people who's behaviour are based on similar belives
you learn socially which parts of belives to follow and which you shouldn't.
When some one tries to reason out those belives they loose the immunity they
loose the immunity they have gained from the herd and try to apply the rules
where where they shouldn't be used. EY puts is pretty well "rationality (is) a
failure of compartmentalization - the attempt to take everything you hear
seriously."&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/reason_as_memetic_immune_disorder.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2016 05:22:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Machine Bias</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/machine_bias.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are two lessons I take out of this story:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote Free Software, Free as in Free Speech, rather mandate their use in
such cases. Even Free Software can also be biased but in case of non free
software it can become practically impossible to find their biases and
correct them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We as should selling algorithms as magic, instead of saying there is 60
likelihood that person X will commit the crime again, say according to my
system the person X is sixty percent similar to other people who commit the
crime again with my rather transparent definition of similarity. Ram and
Rahim are brother, as brothers of course they are similar at many levels,
Ram has commited a crime does that mean Rahim will do it too?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/machine_bias.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 19:45:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why isn't the NSA a hot topic in the US elections?</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_isnt_nsa_a_hot_topic_in_us_elections.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The article talks about how NSA surveillance should be one of the topics of the
US presidential election but isn't. It compares the situation with Germany
where the population is very privacy conscious. It brings out important facts
but doesn't connect them well, it says that German population is privacy
conscious because of the human rights violation by Eastern Block Germany and
earlier by the Nazi secret police, but it reaches the conclusion that
surveillance isn't a hot topic because it is very nuanced and doesn't make good
catch phrase. But every topic is nuanced if you look deep enough and every
issue has only one answer on the surface. Politicians don't generally aim to
change the norm during the election but rather try to attract a sect of people
who already agrees with her/him. So the question here should be why does the
German population care and US doesn't. Well one of the answers can be history
as the author already mentioned, there have been thought policing in the
McCarthy era too but not sure about the extent to which it affected the white
population. Another important factor should be the corporate influence in
politics and maybe media in America compared to Germany. Corporate surveillance
goes hand in hand in government surveillance, if corporates doesn't support an
issue the issue remains unattractive for the politicians. Also it would be an
interesting exercise to study the relation between the profits a parent company
make through breaches of privacy and its coverage on surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_isnt_nsa_a_hot_topic_in_us_elections.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 15:15:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic Inequality</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/economic_inequality.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Paul started off saying he is interested in inequality because he created
I was half expecting him to "this is what I've done wrong and I want to fix
it". Unfortunately it was another essay to justify "undeserved" wealth in the
hands of startup founders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul's essay fails to look at the dynamics of power and money. The amount of
money someone has is often a proxy for political power in the hand of someone.
Increasing inequality amounts to increasing disbalance in political power.
Concentration of political power is problematic because the powerful influence
things in their in their favor knowingly or unknowlingly ignoring the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue that Paul fails to address is the reason for economic inequality.
The wealth of someone grows exponentially, the money someone has the easier it
will be for them to make even more money. That has nothing to do with how much
"deserving" they are or how much wealth they have. Sure your startups have
helped the world, but that doesn't mean they "deserve" all the wealth they
have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have answer to the problem of inequality, but this doesn't mean the
problem doesn't exist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/economic_inequality.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 19:17:25 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>