<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Harsh Gupta</title><link>http://hargup.in/</link><description>Personal website of Harsh Gupta</description><atom:link href="http://hargup.in/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 15:43:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Normalization of Deviation</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/wtf_wtf_wtf.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;span&gt;&lt;!-- url: http://danluu.com/wat/ --&gt;
&lt;!-- title: Normalization of Deviation --&gt;
&lt;!-- date --&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/wtf_wtf_wtf.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Failed Wikipedia</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_wikipedia.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributors follow power law, the median number of contributors is 1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_wikipedia.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>once_upon_a_jihad</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/once_upon_a_jihad.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This essay provides a facinating account of westners who leave their homes to
fight in middle east, Afghanistan and other places to fight for "jihad". The
highlights that for these people going and fighting in a war is pretty much
like a personal fairly tail&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/once_upon_a_jihad.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>icann</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/icann.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the sheer volume of minutely documented and archived process within ICANN
produces a weird, if unintentional, sleight of hand, one that is familiar to
anyone who’s dealt with any large “open” institution, be it a government or
open source software projects. At a certain scale and scope, radical
transparency becomes a means of achieving near-total inscrutability. Concepts
and policies hide behind jargon, jargon hides behind footnotes explaining
jargon, footnotes are full of new jargon rabbit-holes to leap through in some
dizzying political mash-up of House of Leaves with House of Cards. To tell
someone it’s easy to figure out how ICANN works and what the organization
“really” does by offering them hundreds of pages of PDFs on their website is a
little disingenuous, no matter how many languages those PDFs are available in. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/icann.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>eat_your_own_turtle</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/eat_your_own_turtle.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salespeople  were  experts  in  the  art  of  psychological manipulation,
making the client trade, often against his ow n interest, while being happy
about it and loving them and their company&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Most Intolerant Wins: The Dominance of the Stubborn Minority&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Minority rule:
intransigent will dominate because of assymetry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To Read about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Re-normalization group&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Best worse-case divergence from expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody was fired for contracting IBM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example is language assemtry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do books get banned? How to minority view rule the others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the most intolerant person who imposes virtue on the others precisely
    of that intolerance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most motivated wins&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value of courage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rationality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoiding the unccle point&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regular arithmetic is good only for micro benefits and losses instead of
    macro ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Situations with an absorbing state are very different from the one's without
    it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taleb's argument present interesting argumenta. I should probably try to run
    a simulation for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take maximum risk in everything that does not entertain ruin condition,
but take max precaution in ones who does. -- Same applies to assumption of good
faith norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things that have repeated exposure should never be analyzed as a single
    event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing too much without ability to eliminate junk degrades knowledge. -- My
    efforts at this should be solidifying current knowledge rather than
    absorbing more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intellectual  and  ethical  freedom  requires the absence  of  the  skin  of  others in one’s gam One-dimensional stochastic process always revisits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to own people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conditioning and psycological manipulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forcing people to have something significant to loose if they disobey
    authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to contractors, employees have a significant skin in the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By being employees, the employees signal certain kind of domestication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today a person is employeed by the idea that (s)he needs t obe employable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best slave is someone you overpay and who know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traders and salespeople were only managable when they were unprofitable, in
    which case they weren't wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foul Language as a signal of being free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't signal competence if you don't take risks for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What matters isn't what a person has or doesn't have; it is what he or she is
    afraid of losing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easier to trust the word of an autocrat than a fragile elected
    official.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people have something to loose they loose courage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disorder increases with dimentionality&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://medium.com/@nntaleb/commencement-address-american-university-in-beirut-2016-a5c6d57984b#.p12llhkhd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success is antifragile&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;International Association of Name Droppers :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/eat_your_own_turtle.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>digital_activism</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/digital_activism.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technology by itself is not enough we need to leverage it to create the
  effect we want it to have&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lumia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Democracy OS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/digital_activism.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>bullshit</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/bullshit.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A lot of bullshit happens because people don't know what they are talking about&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bullshit is not a matter of concealing the truth, it is about manipulating the
audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bullshit is vague, &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/bullshit.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2017 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Community vs Compliance</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/community_vs_compliance.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This a very interesting discussion about GPL law suits and GPL enforcement. The
main point of debate is whether to use law suits to enforce GPL or not. Both of
the parties agree that having upstream contributions and user freedoms are
important but disagree about the particular methods to pursue that goal. The
side which pushes for law suits or threats argue that otherwise companies won't
comply, we don't get the code back and users loose on freedom. The other side
argues that law suits or their threats turn companies into law suits turn
companies into enemies. They are less likely to coorperate, meaning worse
software. Instead the way should be through internal negotiations, and changing
the culture from inside, companies eventually do contribute upstream they also
benifit from it and also because the law requires them to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal opinion is that GPL is important, and the possibility of existance
of a law suit. If a company is going very antagonistic there needs to be a law
suits because otherwise when the companies know that no one realistic change of
law suit then GPL is powerless. Stallman himself gave examples of cases where
they were able to get GPL compliance simply about asking companies to do and
telling them that they are legally required to do so. So to me the question is
really about threshold, not the fact that they should be law suit or not,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway as Linus says it is often easier to change things by working with your
opponents rathan working against them but against them should appear like a
realistic senario when things don't work out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/community_vs_compliance.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Aug 2016 21:38:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Streetlight Effect: A metaphor for knowledge and ignorance</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/streetlight_effect.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This was a fascinating piece about Streetlight Effect and using it a as
metaphor to describe knowledge and ignorance. The really interesting bit was
where author described totalitarianism as something where there is only one
view point be it of boilerplate Marxism or free market capitalism or anything.
The totalitarian view point assumes that their framework can explain it all and
everything else. Totalitarianism is the like the streetlight where you try to
find all your answers but they don't exist there. The opposite of
totalitarianism isn't another view point but darkness where good and bad aren't
well defined and where the difference of between truth and false is not known.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/streetlight_effect.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 06:12:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Another rant about academia and open source</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/another_rant_about_academia_and_open_source.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; You can win in two ways: you can research something that helps somebody beat
&amp;gt; somebody else up or consume more, so that they give you funding. Or you can win
&amp;gt; by not losing, by pulling some wild theoretical stunt that puts you out of
&amp;gt; range of everybody else so that they can’t come after you. You become good at
&amp;gt; critiquing things in ways that sound smart, and tell people who disagree with
&amp;gt; you that they haven’t read your cannon. You hope that if they call your bluff
&amp;gt; and read it, they will be so converted by the experience that they will leave
&amp;gt; you alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This para drives home the point at so many levels. This is also something I
need to be really careful while doing inter disciplinary research. Being from
computational sciences I can use tools which no one in the humanities area
understand and it will be trying to answer questions which no one in the area
of the computational science cares about. So you'll be virtually unbeatable,
which is a really bad place to be in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping your research in open and helping access it as much as possible not
only increases the value of your research but also gives a proof that what you
are working on is something somebody cares about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/another_rant_about_academia_and_open_source.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 05:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>