<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Harsh's blog</title><link>https://hargup.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://hargup.github.io/rss.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 01:40:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola &lt;http://getnikola.com/&gt;</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>GSoC 2014 with Sympy</title><link>https://hargup.github.io/posts/gsoc-2014-with-sympy.html</link><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi, I'm Harsh Gupta a undergrad student at IIT Kharagpur, I'm a Google Summer
of Code student with Sympy. It is a requirement from my organisation to write
regular blog posts about the work and I've been procrastinating on the blog all
along. Probably because of the fear of being "wrong" in front of
hundred's of potential reader. But it is ridiculous to not to attempt because of the fact
that you can fail. And it is important to let the world know about your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, What is a Google Summer of Code?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Summer of Code is a program by Google to promote opensource development.
In this program Google pays handsome stipends to students to work for various opensource
organisations. In the application phase the students have to write proposals to
the organisations describing the projects they want to do with the organisation
and how do they fit for it. If the proposal is accepted the student is provided
with a mentor and with the guidance of the mentor the student has to complete
the project in the given timeline. You can look at my proposal &lt;!-- Link to the
proposal --&gt;. I proposed to work on improving the current equation solvers in
Sympy. My mentors for the Project are Matthew Rocklin &lt;!-- Link --&gt; and Sergey
B Kiperchev &lt;!-- Link  --&gt; &lt;!-- verify the name --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A word about Sympy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sympy &lt;!-- Link --&gt; is a pure python library for symbolic computation. Symbolic
computation is similar to the maths you do by hands and it differs from
numerical computations. More about Symbolic and Numerical computation in the
next post. Sympy has been created by hundreds of contributors starting from 2006.
It has a awesome developer
community and we encourage outsiders to contribute and get their hands dirty with
the code. What do you need to start contributing? Some python skills and little
patience. Download the latest development code. &lt;!-- Link --&gt;
Go through the development workflow &lt;!-- Link --&gt;. Find something to work on
&lt;!-- Link --&gt;. Code it and send us a pull request. Happy Coding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://hargup.github.io/posts/gsoc-2014-with-sympy.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 00:54:22 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>