<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Harsh Gupta (Posts about thought)</title><link>http://hargup.in/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://hargup.in/categories/thought.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 19:15:34 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>"On Thinking and Stimulated Thinking"</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/stimulated_thinking.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a distinction between two modes of working, one is the "explore
mode", you need to put in a lot of effort, and be concious while you are doing
something. This which occurs while you are learning something, say learning to
drive a car or bike. Other mode is the "habit mode" where you are able to do
something, effortlessly without thinking because you have done it so many
times, like riding a bike after you have learned it, or even writing or typing
which I am doing now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of the article is that "real thinking" happens in the "explore
mode", you are deliberate, you are explicative, you are curious, you (at least
mentally) try a lot of things out and reach a conclusion. What a lot of people
end up doing is they go do "stimulated thinking", which often looks and acts
like thinking but is actually in the "habit mode".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Stimulated thinking" is dangerous because is not flexible, it cannot
understand things deeply or see how they will change if the context will
change. Simply "Stimulated thinking" is not thinking and should not pass as so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explore mode requires action and reaction in an environment, where the person
exploring something decides how to act and then modifies her behavior on the
basis of the reaction of the environment. Habit "knows" what is the reaction
will be so it behaves accordingly in fixed patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Author claims that so much of our learning process today is about broadcast,
not action and reaction or learning by trying something out. Education is
formal broadcast, so is TV or social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see parallels here with "Amusing Ourselves to Death" where Niel Postman (in
part) talks that TV consumption is passive, from few to many, there is no
creativity and interactivity for the consumers of television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noam Chomsky also said "You just don't let a book pass from the front of your
eyes". Well to avoid stimulated thinking I am here again writing webnotes. It
takes effort but I guess after sometime I'll be in the habit of putting in this
effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just clarifying that there is nothing wrong with habits per se, I'm able to
type only after I have deliberately learned this habit of typing and without
it, a lot of my effort would have gone into the act of typing itself instead
thinking about what I am writing. The problem is which thinking that you are
thinking but you are actually not.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>thought</category><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/stimulated_thinking.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Aug 2018 19:04:55 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>