<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Harsh Gupta (Posts about webnotes)</title><link>http://hargup.in/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://hargup.in/categories/webnotes.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 07:10:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Streetlight Effect: A metaphor for knowledge and ignorance</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/streetlight_effect.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This was a fascinating piece about Streetlight Effect and using it a as
metaphor to describe knowledge and ignorance. The really interesting bit was
where author described totalitarianism as something where there is only one
view point be it of boilerplate Marxism or free market capitalism or anything.
The totalitarian view point assumes that their framework can explain it all and
everything else. Totalitarianism is the like the streetlight where you try to
find all your answers but they don't exist there. The opposite of
totalitarianism isn't another view point but darkness where good and bad aren't
well defined and where the difference of between truth and false is not known.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/streetlight_effect.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 06:12:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Another rant about academia and open source</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/another_rant_about_academia_and_open_source.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; You can win in two ways: you can research something that helps somebody beat
&amp;gt; somebody else up or consume more, so that they give you funding. Or you can win
&amp;gt; by not losing, by pulling some wild theoretical stunt that puts you out of
&amp;gt; range of everybody else so that they can’t come after you. You become good at
&amp;gt; critiquing things in ways that sound smart, and tell people who disagree with
&amp;gt; you that they haven’t read your cannon. You hope that if they call your bluff
&amp;gt; and read it, they will be so converted by the experience that they will leave
&amp;gt; you alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This para drives home the point at so many levels. This is also something I
need to be really careful while doing inter disciplinary research. Being from
computational sciences I can use tools which no one in the humanities area
understand and it will be trying to answer questions which no one in the area
of the computational science cares about. So you'll be virtually unbeatable,
which is a really bad place to be in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping your research in open and helping access it as much as possible not
only increases the value of your research but also gives a proof that what you
are working on is something somebody cares about.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/another_rant_about_academia_and_open_source.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 05:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why isn't the NSA a hot topic in the US elections?</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_isnt_nsa_a_hot_topic_in_us_elections.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The article talks about how NSA surveillance should be one of the topics of the
US presidential election but isn't. It compares the situation with Germany
where the population is very privacy conscious. It brings out important facts
but doesn't connect them well, it says that German population is privacy
conscious because of the human rights violation by Eastern Block Germany and
earlier by the Nazi secret police, but it reaches the conclusion that
surveillance isn't a hot topic because it is very nuanced and doesn't make good
catch phrase. But every topic is nuanced if you look deep enough and every
issue has only one answer on the surface. Politicians don't generally aim to
change the norm during the election but rather try to attract a sect of people
who already agrees with her/him. So the question here should be why does the
German population care and US doesn't. Well one of the answers can be history
as the author already mentioned, there have been thought policing in the
McCarthy era too but not sure about the extent to which it affected the white
population. Another important factor should be the corporate influence in
politics and maybe media in America compared to Germany. Corporate surveillance
goes hand in hand in government surveillance, if corporates doesn't support an
issue the issue remains unattractive for the politicians. Also it would be an
interesting exercise to study the relation between the profits a parent company
make through breaches of privacy and its coverage on surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/why_isnt_nsa_a_hot_topic_in_us_elections.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 15:15:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic Inequality</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/economic_inequality.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Paul started off saying he is interested in inequality because he created
I was half expecting him to "this is what I've done wrong and I want to fix
it". Unfortunately it was another essay to justify "undeserved" wealth in the
hands of startup founders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul's essay fails to look at the dynamics of power and money. The amount of
money someone has is often a proxy for political power in the hand of someone.
Increasing inequality amounts to increasing disbalance in political power.
Concentration of political power is problematic because the powerful influence
things in their in their favor knowingly or unknowlingly ignoring the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue that Paul fails to address is the reason for economic inequality.
The wealth of someone grows exponentially, the money someone has the easier it
will be for them to make even more money. That has nothing to do with how much
"deserving" they are or how much wealth they have. Sure your startups have
helped the world, but that doesn't mean they "deserve" all the wealth they
have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have answer to the problem of inequality, but this doesn't mean the
problem doesn't exist.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/economic_inequality.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 19:17:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Normalization of Deviation</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/normailization_of_deviation.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was a pretty well written post about how very messed up practices end up
normalized. The answer is a weird combinatin of over optimism, rationalization
and adaption. And when a messed up practice gets normalized it is very hard to
see what's wrong with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very simply solution that Atul Gawande talked about in the Checklist
Manifesto is to have a checklist. In the book he compared the medical sector
and infrastucture/construction sector. Both fields are immensely complex but
medicial practitioners often end up making terrible mistakes, which includes
cases like the one where a surgen forgot her equipment in the patient, where as
in construction error which have any harm to human life are very very rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you don't have checklist for every small thing, and Atul provided a
guideline to making checklist, I don't clearly remember and I should go and
read the sections of the book again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checklists are useful because they end up freeing your mind from the
unnecessary boring detail. there are also other cases I can think of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to apply a rule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where the rewards or looses of doing something occur only in long term, we
tend to ignore the long term result and focus on instant gratification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always and never rules&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The projects the complete counts and not the one you start.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formalization leads to gramatization, when a formal structure is in place it is
harder see things in informal terms or whatever that doesn't fall into that
formal structure tends to get ignored. A very clear example will be case where
peolple who have only learned about information transfer uses of language tend
find phatic usuages like that of small talk "useless".  But as it evident from
the use of term phatic, the way we with problems of formalization is more
formalization trying to capture things which weren't captured earlier, ofcourse
that formalization also leaves something. But as it said in Statistics, all
models are false but some are useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/normailization_of_deviation.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 18:46:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>You're only 23 stop rushing life</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/you_re_only_23.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;We are young, energetic and ambitious but impatient. We want to "successful",
fast. Success is defined relative to the "success" of our peers which gives a
feeling that if we are not rushing things we are "falling behind". In our
definition success is a race. When you are running a race you can't stop to see
if this race is something worth running for. In the "race of life" everybody is
a looser. I think I can also say "in any race of life everybody is a looser".&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/you_re_only_23.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2015 19:49:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Let's not let fear defeat our Values</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/let_fear_not_defeat_our_values.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently American Presidential candidate Donal Trump called out for a total ban on Muslim immigration to America. It is great to see that Sundar Pichai, the CEO of Google, come out and speak against it. I totally support his statement that people like him, people who are privileged should speak up for people who are not so privileged because whose voices are often not included in the debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First they came for the Socialists, and I did not speak out because I was
not a Socialist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then they came for the Trade Unionists, and I did not speak out because I
was not a Trade Unionist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then they came for the Jews, and I did not speak out because I was not a
Jew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then they came for me and there was no one left to speak for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Martin Niemöller&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/let_fear_not_defeat_our_values.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2015 19:16:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Non-Programmer’s Apology</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/a_non_programmers_apology.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I pretty much agree with Aaron here. Why am I still doing programming? Because
the programming I do is easy and it gets paid well and it is very uncomfortable
to move to newer areas, especially because they involve a lot of uncertaintly.
But do I want to do programming for life? Programming is great and powerful
tool but programming as end of things is not something that I want. I can learn
the new skills with time, I guess this time it is important that I don't take
pure programming jobs, or else it will become harder and harded to come out of
comfort zone. Take computational social science or ethics or civics intern and
more policy and social issue and please keep writing and share your writings.
You'll be misrepresented/misunderstood a few times, but its okay thats the way
you'll learn.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/a_non_programmers_apology.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 20:56:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Surprising Problem of Too Much Talent</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/too_much_talent.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The study from some sports suggests that add more talented people decreases the
overall team performance probably due to decreased coversion in the team. I
guess the problem is more because of hiring assholes rather than hiring talent.
People skills and physical/sports/domain ability often don't come together.
And as suggested by _&amp;lt;stegasourous strategy&amp;gt;, in some areas assholery appears
more clever (say talented).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/too_much_talent.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 10:42:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The problem with Female SuperHeros</title><link>http://hargup.in/webnotes/problem_with_female_superheroes.html</link><dc:creator>Harsh Gupta</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The article summarized a research which found that exposure to a 13 minute clip
featuring the Damsel in distress trop reduced the gender egalitarian views of
the participant and exposure of hypersexualized female characters reduced their
body esteem. To me the results were not unexpected. The comments thread wasn't
unexpected either. A lot of people were saying why there are studying the
effect on only women and not on men. Others were saying men are sexualized too.
Both are valid propositions if they are poposed as extension of research but
totally unvalid in the context because they were used to discredit the
research. Just because men suffer doesn't mean the sufferings of men and women
are equal and the problems of women are not worth the attention.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>webnotes</category><guid>http://hargup.in/webnotes/problem_with_female_superheroes.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 10:24:06 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>